Albert Warren Stearns Papers MS078
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Albert Warren Stearns Papers
1697 -- 1937
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Stearns, Albert Warren
MS078
3.2 Linear Feet 3 boxes and 4 oversized folders
Arrangement
This collection is organized in one series
Scope and Contents
This collection contains two boxes of newspaper clippings collected by Albert Warren Stearns. The articles were cut from publications dating from 1697 to 1937. The clippings are grouped according to specific subjects assigned by Stearns. The content of the articles reflect Stearns' sociological interests, and cover topics such as crime, prisons, health, and welfare.
Biographical / Historical
Albert Warren Stearns (1885-1959), A1906, M1910, H1943, served as the seventh Dean of the Tufts College Medical School from 1927 to 1945. He was the first Tufts alumnus to hold that office.
Stearns was born on January 26, 1885 in Billerica, Massachusetts. He attended public schools there and left to work in a hardware store shortly before his high school graduation. In 1905, he met a member of the Tufts staff who persuaded him to enter the college. He arrived at East Hall for the start of the academic year with his neighbor and fellow Tufts student, Michael Neson, in a horse-drawn carriage, piled high with furniture. After graduation, Stearns decided to attend Tufts Medical School, expressing interest in the neurological sciences. He received his medical degree in 1910. In 1911, he became a resident at Danvers State Hospital, moving the following year to Boston State Hospital. In 1912, he married Frances Matsell Judkins, with whom he had two children.
By 1913, Stearns was practicing neurology and psychiatry and from 1923 to 1927, he served as consultant to the US Naval Hospital in Chelsea, MA. He returned to Tufts Medical School in 1927 as a professor of psychiatry and Dean of the school, a position he held until he became a professor and Chairman of the Department of Sociology in Arts and Sciences (1945-1955).
From 1929 to 1933, Stearns served as commissioner of the Department of Correction of Massachusetts. He also acted as Associate Commissioner of the Department of Mental Diseases for the state from 1935 to 1945. He served in the Medical Corps of the US Navy in both World War I and World War II (on leave for that purpose from 1942 to 1945). He held prominent positions in several psychiatric and medical organizations. He authored a number of works, including "Personality of Criminals," published in 1932. In 1945, Tufts awarded him the honorary degree, Doctor of Science. Stearns died unexpectedly in his hometown on September 24, 1959.
One of Stearns's sons, Charles Edward Stearns, was a professor of geology and dean of Tufts College of Liberal Arts from 1954 to 1967 and 1968 to 1969. The Stearns Building, located at 120 Harrison Avenue on the Boston Campus and formerly known as the Eclipse Building, was named in his memory in 1963.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Dept. of Sociology; Faculty papers; Stearns, Albert Warren
- Reference material, 1697 -- 1937; MS078.001; 3.6 Linear Feet
  Scope and Contents
  This series includes Stearns' clippings from newspaper, magazines, and brochures. The material in this collection dates from 1697 to 1937, and is arranged by topic. Topics include crime, cartoons, prisons, insanity, welfare, and New England crime history. The category "cartoons" includes political cartoons relating to Stearns' research. There is also a large grouping of uncategorized articles, though the majority of these articles also relate to crime or mental health. Aside from articles and political cartoons, many subject files also include maps and diagrams, also from published sources, of state hospitals and prisons. These materials probably served as reference files for Stearns' sociological studies of crime.
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged alphabetically.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Open for research.
  - Crime articles (1 of 6), 1823 -- 1936; MS078.001.001.00001 (Box 1)
  - Crime articles (2 of 6), 1823 -- 1936; MS078.001.001.00002 (Box 1)
  - Crime articles (3 of 6), 1823 -- 1936; MS078.001.001.00003 (Box 1)
  - Crime articles (4 of 6), 1823 -- 1936; MS078.001.001.00004 (Box 1)
  - Crime articles (5 of 6), 1823 -- 1936; MS078.001.001.00005 (Box 1)
  - Crime articles (6 of 6), 1823 -- 1936; MS078.001.001.00006 (Box 1)
  - Political cartoons (1 of 5), 1860 -- 1888; MS078.001.001.00007 (Box 1)
  - Political cartoons (2 of 5), 1860 -- 1888; MS078.001.001.00008 (Box 1)
  - Political cartoons (3 of 5), 1860 -- 1888; MS078.001.001.00009 (Box 1)
  - Political cartoons (4 of 5), 1860 -- 1888; MS078.001.001.00010 (Box 1)
  - Political cartoons (5 of 5), 1860 -- 1888; MS078.001.001.00011 (Box 1)
  - Health articles (1 of 3), 1847 -- 1876; MS078.001.001.00012 (Box 1)
  - Health articles (2 of 3), 1847 -- 1876; MS078.001.001.00013 (Box 1)
  - Health articles (3 of 3), 1847 -- 1876; MS078.001.001.00014 (Box 1)
  - Insanity articles (1 of 2), 1814 -- 1937; MS078.001.001.00015 (Box 1)
  - Insanity articles (2 of 2), 1814 -- 1937; MS078.001.001.00016 (Box 1)
  - Prison articles (1 of 7), 1737 -- 1933; MS078.001.001.00017 (Box 1)
  - Prison articles (2 of 7), 1737 -- 1933; MS078.001.001.00018 (Box 1)
  - Prison articles (3 of 7), 1737 -- 1933; MS078.001.001.00019 (Box 1)
  - Prison articles (4 of 7), 1737 -- 1933; MS078.001.001.00020 (Box 1)
  - Prison articles (5 of 7), 1737 -- 1933; MS078.001.002.00001 (Box 2)
  - Prison articles (6 of 7), 1737 -- 1933; MS078.001.002.00002 (Box 2)
  - Prison articles (7 of 7), 1737 -- 1933; MS078.001.002.00003 (Box 2)
  - New England crime history articles (1 of 7), 1697 -- 1852; MS078.001.002.00004 (Box 2)
  - New England crime history articles (2 of 7), 1697 -- 1852; MS078.001.002.00005 (Box 2)
  - New England crime history articles (3 of 7), 1697 -- 1852; MS078.001.002.00006 (Box 2)
  - New England crime history articles (4 of 7), 1697 -- 1852; MS078.001.002.00007 (Box 2)
  - New England crime history articles (5 of 7), 1697 -- 1852; MS078.001.002.00008 (Box 2)
  - New England crime history articles (6 of 7), 1697 -- 1852; MS078.001.002.00009 (Box 2)
  - New England crime history articles (7 of 7), 1697 -- 1852; MS078.001.002.00010 (Box 2)
  - Welfare articles (1 of 10), 1823 -- 1899; MS078.001.002.00011 (Box 2)
  - Welfare articles (2 of 10), 1823 -- 1899; MS078.001.002.00012 (Box 2)
  - Welfare articles (3 of 10), 1823 -- 1899; MS078.001.002.00013 (Box 2)
  - Welfare articles (4 of 10), 1823 -- 1899; MS078.001.002.00014 (Box 2)
  - Welfare articles (5 of 10), 1823 -- 1899; MS078.001.002.00015 (Box 2)
  - Welfare articles (6 of 10), 1823 -- 1899; MS078.001.002.00016 (Box 2)
  - Welfare articles (7 of 10), 1823 -- 1899; MS078.001.002.00017 (Box 2)
  - Welfare articles (8 of 10), 1823 -- 1899; MS078.001.002.00018 (Box 2)
  - Welfare articles (9 of 10), 1823 -- 1899; MS078.001.003.00001 (Box 3)
  - Welfare articles (10 of 10), 1823 -- 1899; MS078.001.003.00002 (Box 3)
  - Unlabeled articles (1 of 10), 1765 -- 1907; MS078.001.003.00003 (Box 3)
  - Unlabeled articles (2 of 10), 1765 -- 1907; MS078.001.003.00004 (Box 3)
  - Unlabeled articles (3 of 10), 1765 -- 1907; MS078.001.003.00005 (Box 3)
  - Unlabeled articles (4 of 10), 1765 -- 1907; MS078.001.003.00006 (Box 3)
  - Unlabeled articles (5 of 10), 1765 -- 1907; MS078.001.003.00007 (Box 3)
  - Unlabeled articles (6 of 10), 1765 -- 1907; MS078.001.003.00008 (Box 3)
  - Unlabeled articles (7 of 10), 1765 -- 1907; MS078.001.003.00009 (Box 3)
  - Unlabeled articles (8 of 10), 1765 -- 1907; MS078.001.003.00010 (Box 3)
  - Unlabeled articles (9 of 10), 1765 -- 1907; MS078.001.003.00011 (Box 3)
  - Unlabeled articles (10 of 10), 1765 -- 1907; MS078.001.003.00012 (Box 3)
  - Crime articles, 1823 -- 1936; MS078.001.004.00001 (Box Small Map Case 2 Drawer 1)
  - Prison articles, 1737 -- 1933; MS078.001.004.00002 (Box Small Map Case 2 Drawer 1)
  - Welfare articles, 1823 -- 1899; MS078.001.004.00003 (Box Small Map Case 2 Drawer 1)
  - Unlabeled articles, 1765 -- 1907; MS078.001.004.00004 (Box Small Map Case 2 Drawer 1)